Guide to the Joanne Landy Papers TAM.785
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Joanne Landy Papers
1967-2017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harrison, Tom
Landy, Joanne
TAM.785
2.48 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 oversize folder.
2.655 Gigabytes in 25 files.
11 audiocassettes 9 compact cassettes and 2 micro cassettes.
This collection consists of correspondence, flyers, and administrative files related to socialist activist Joanne Landy's work as an editor for New Politics magazine and as an organizer for the Campaign for Peace and Democracy. The materials cover the editorial and administrative processes involved in publishing New Politics during the 1980s through the early 2000s and the social and intellectual context of the advocacy Landy organized with the Campaign for Peace and Democracy. The files are both paper and electronic, though the majority of the records are paper. The files on the Campaign for Peace and Democracy include audio and video recordings of talks by Landy pertaining to the organization's activism.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Tom Harrison in January 2019, the accession number associated with this donation is 2019.049.
Arrangement
Collection was organized into two series. Series I: New Politics Correspondences and Administrative Records and Series II: Campaign for Peace and Democracy. Correspondence files in Series I were arranged in order by last name of correspondent. Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera files in Series II were kept in chronological order by year.
Biographical Note
Joanne Landy (1941-2017) was a writer, editor, and activist associated with the "Third Camp" socialist movement, who critiqued authoritarianism in nations on both sides of the Cold War. A student activist in the 1960s, Landy went on to be a longstanding member of the editorial board for the socialist magazine New Politics. In 1982, she co-founded the Campaign for Peace and Democracy, an international leftist solidarity movement advocating for egalitarian democratic socialism.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of activist and writer Joanne Landy's files on her editorial work at New Politics magazine and her activist work as co-director of the Campaign for Peace and Democracy. The files on New Politics reflect Landy's work on the magazine's editorial board in the 1980s through the 2000s, including correspondence with subscribers, writers, and other members of the editorial board, alongside meeting minutes and other administrative records pertaining to the magazine. The files on the Campaign for Peace and Democracy include flyers for events and protests, clippings, correspondence, electronic records, audio recordings, and video recordings related to the organization's progressive anti-war international activism starting from the 1980s until Landy's death in 2017.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Appraisal
2 blank CD-Rs and 1 installation CD-R were discarded. In September 2024, 1 blank audiocassette was deaccessioned.
Born-digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Libraries/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Socialism -- New York (State).; Peace movements -- United States.; Social democracy; Journalism, Socialist -- United States; Solidarity; Clippings (information artifacts); Harrison, Tom; Campaign for Peace and Democracy
- Series I: New Politics Correspondences and Administrative Records, 1967-2000
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains correspondences and various administrative records of the New Politics publication, including editorial board minutes and copyright certificates.
  - Correspondence: Stanley Aronwitz, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: John Bloom, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Sam Bottome, 1987-1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Paul Buhle, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Raymond Challinor, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Robert Cummings, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Ernest Erber, 1984-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Gertrude Ezorsky, 1988-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Ernie Haberkern, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Herbert Hill, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Alan Johnson, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Arthur Lipon, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Stanford Lyman, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Marvin Mandell, 1988-1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Scott McLemee, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: George Meany, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Christopher Phelps, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Alan Wald, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Michael Wreszin, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Jim Young, 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: "Cuckoo" Letters, 1975-1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: General, 1986-2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Interviews with Phillis Jacobson and Julius Jacobson, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Advertising, 1986-1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Historic Documents, 1967-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Reprint Requests, 1987-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Editorial Board Minutes, 1984-2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Fund Appeals, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Copyright Certificates, 1988-2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Intellectual Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Campaign for Peace and Democracy, 1980-2017
  Series II contains documents pertaining to the Campaign for Peace and Democracy. The series consists mostly of flyers, clippings, and ephemera from events and actions. Series also contains audiocassettes and digital files.
  - Posters, 1987-1993 (Box Shared Tamiment 054, Folder 3)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 10, Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2011 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2013 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2014 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2015 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, 2016 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Flyers, Clippings, and Ephemera, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Joanne Landy on American Public Health Association, 1980-12 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Joanne Landy on Tuberculosis, 1980-05-15 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Joanne Landy on Polish Healthcare, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - MacArthur Proposal, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - MacArthur Grant, 1986-1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters of Support, 1988-1994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Detente From Below -- Virginia Baron, undated; cuid43090 (Box 4, Audiocassette cuid43090)
  - Joanne Landy on the Soviet Union, December 1, 1984; cuid43091 (Box 4, Audiocassette cuid43091)
  - Joanne Landy and Norman Solomon, 1985; cuid43092 (Box 4, Audiocassette cuid43092)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Distorted audio
  - Joanne Landy on Bob Grant Program, undated; cuid43088 (Box 4, Audiocassette cuid43088)
  - Joanne Landy on Poland, September 27, 1981; cuid43087 (Box 4, Audiocassette cuid43087A, cuid43087B, cuid43087C, cuid43087D)
    Muddy audio on third audiocassette
  - Joanne Landy on WBAI Radio, March 23, 1987; cuid43086 (Box 4, Audiocassette cuid43086)
  - "Solidarity", November 8, 1981; cuid43089 (Box 4, Audiocassette cuid43089)
  - Rally at Palazzo delle Esposizioni, 2011-10; TW_TAM_785_ER_1
  - Turning the Tide Presentation by Friends for a Nonviolent World, 2009-02-21; TW_TAM_785_ER_2